国际空间站是太空中最大的人造结构
The International Space Station is the largest man-made structure in space.
它在地面一件件造好，发射到太空，然后在轨组装
It was built in pieces and then launched into space and assembled in orbit.
本期视频我想带大家详细了解下国际空间站
In this video, I want to give you a detailed look at the station.
我们将了解每一个组件的组装顺序
We're gonna look at each module in the order that they were assembled.
我们还将了解参与其中的国家，与其未来对空间站的计划
We'll look at the countries involved and the future plans for the station.
准备好了吗？一起造个空间站吧！
So if you're ready, let's go build a space station.
国际空间站，简称ISS，花了很多很多年才变成现实
The International Space Station, or ISS, took many years to become a reality.
1984年，美国开启了空间站自由计划
In 1984, the United States announced a project called Space Station Freedom.
这有一张最初空间站的构想图
Here's some drawings of what the original station might have looked like.
这个最初构想的空间站并未建造
It was never actually built in its original form.
其间有过很多次修改设计，经费也被美国国会砍没了
There were lots of redesigns, and it's funding was almost completely cut by US Congress.
之后到了1993年，在其他几个国家参与进来之后
Then in 1993, after several other countries were brought on board,
名字就正式变成了“国际空间站”
the name was officially changed to the International Space Station.
五年后，它在太空中“动工”了
Five years later, construction begins in space.
我稍后会向你展示完整的建造过程
I'll show you the complete construction process,
但首先，我们先稍微了解下ISS的大致信息
but first, let's learn a little bit more about the station.
ISS现在长这样
This is the ISS as it looks today.
它主要用于做一些只能在太空进行的科学实验
It's mainly used to conduct science experiments that can only be done in space.
空间站常驻6人
There's usually six astronauts on board the station.
通常每6个月一轮换以保证不会有人在上面呆太久
They generally switch out about every six months so that no one spends too much time in space.
ISS大小相当于一个美式橄榄球场
The station is about the size of an American football field.
高度在地球大气边缘
It's located just outside the Earth's atmosphere.
轨道称为近地轨道
This is called Low Earth Orbit.
相比于同步卫星，它的位置不是很高
It's not very high up, considering that some satellites orbit way out here.
ISS每92分钟绕地球一圈
The ISS only takes about 92 minutes to orbit the earth.
速度约每小时28000公里
That's about 28,000 kilometers per hour.
ISS会（因空气阻力而）随着时间的推移降低高度
Over time, the ISS will slowly lose altitude.
如果放任不管，它最终会落回地球大气烧毁
If nothing was done, the station would eventually burn up as it reenters the Earth's atmosphere.
为防止其发生，空间站要定期进行推进以维持轨道
To prevent this, the station must be periodically reboosted to stay in space.
ISS主要参与建设者有美国
The main countries now participating are United States,
加拿大、俄罗斯、日本及许多欧空局的国家
Canada, Russia, Japan and many countries from the European Space Agency.
接下来看下ISS的主要部分
Let's get to know the main parts of the station.
综合桁架结构是ISS的“脊梁骨”
The Integrated Truss Structure is kind of like the backbone of the station.
它上面有产生电力的太阳帆板
It holds the solar arrays to generate electricity,
还有用于为站上设备散热的散热板
radiator panels, these remove heat from the station,
还有其他一些设备和科学仪器
and other equipment and science experiments are also attached.
剩下的这部分包含加压的舱段
This part down here contains the pressurized modules,
宇航员不穿宇航服就可以在里面工作
which means the astronauts can live and work in here without a space suit.
所有来自俄罗斯的舱段构成了“俄罗斯区”
All of the Russian modules make up the Russian Orbital Segment.
另一部分就叫“美国区”
The other side is called the United States Orbital Segment.
它由美国、欧洲、日本、加拿大建造的组件构成
It's made up of modules from the United States, Europe, Japan and Canada.
ISS的不同舱段在全世界的很多地方建造
The different pieces of the station, also called modules, were built in many locations around the globe.
每个舱段最后被以下三种火箭之一发射进太空
Each module was then launched into space by one of these three rockets,
它们是美国的航天飞机、俄罗斯的质子号火箭和联盟号火箭
the American Space Shuttle, the Russian Proton Rocket and the Russian Soyuz Rocket.
到了太空就该组装了
Once in space, it's time to put it all together.
这可比拼乐高难多了
This is definitely not your average Lego set.
ISS从建造开始到基本建成花了十多年
Once construction started, the ISS took a little over a decade before it was considered complete.
时间轴上每条黄线都代表有新的舱段被安装到空间站上
Each one of these lines represents the addition of a new module to the station.
那么咱们从头来看看吧
Let's go ahead and start at the very beginning.
ISS第一个舱段是俄罗斯的曙光号功能货舱
The first piece of the station is a Russian module called Zarya.
它由太阳帆板供电，还可以为空间站提供推进动力
It provides power from the solar arrays and also propulsion when there's a need to move the station.
前部有三个对接口，后部有一个
There's three docking ports in front and one in back.
它们将用于连接空间站之后的组件
These will be used to connect to the next pieces of the station.
第二个舱段是来自美国的团结号，或者叫节点舱1
The second module is American, and it's called Unity, or Node 1.
它有六个对接口用于连接未来的舱段
It has six docking ports to connect to future modules.
两种不同的对接口还有个特殊的适配器
There's a special piece here to connect between the different docking mechanisms.
称为加压对接适配舱，简称PMA
This is called a Pressurized Mating Adapter, or PMA for short.
团结号是和PMA-1、PMA-2共同发射的
Unity was launched with PMA-1 and PMA-2.
接下来是星辰号服务舱
This is the Zvezda service module.
它提供生命保障系统，是“俄罗斯区”的功能中心
It provides life support systems and is considered the functional center of the Russian Orbital Segment.
它也是前面三个对接口，后面一个
It also has three docking ports in front and one in back.
接下来是Z1桁架
Next is the Z1 Truss.
它可以放置ISS的设备
This holds equipment for the station.
虽然不属于主桁架，但它提供了一个暂时的放置平台
It's not part of the main truss, but it provided a temporary mounting place,
之后我们会看到
as we'll see here in a moment.
然后PMA-3安装到了团结号的下方
PMA-3 was then added to the bottom side of Unity.
备份一个放着总没坏处
It's always good to have an extra one of these around.
P6桁架暂时放在Z1桁架上方
The P6 Truss was temporarily mounted to the top of the Z1 Truss.
它上面有第一组太阳帆板
This includes the first solar array wings.
它为正在如火如荼建造的空间站提供了大量电力
This provides much needed power to the growing station.
上面还有散热板，来为空间站散热
Radiator panels were also installed to help remove excess heat from the station.
从现在开始，空间站功能齐全了，宇航员可以长期驻留于此
At this point, there was enough functionality that astronauts can start living aboard the station,
而不再是短期访问了
instead of just temporary visits.
从2000年11月至今
From November 2000 until now,
空间站一直都有人值守，从未间断
there has been a continuous human presence on board the station.
命运号也叫美国实验舱
The Destiny module is also called the US Laboratory.
这里可以进行大量科学研究
This is a place where a lot of scientific research happens.
它在安装的时候稍微调整了一下PMA-2的位置
A little rearranging was necessary so that Destiny could be installed.
2001年3月，外部储物平台1(ESP-1)安装
March 2001 came the addition of the External Stowage Platform 1, or ESP-1.
这里储存空间站的备用零件
This was a place to store spare parts for the station.
加拿大为加拿大臂2的建造做出了主要贡献
Canada made a vital contribution with the Canadarm2.
它是一组可以在空间站外提供辅助的机械臂
It's a robotic arm that can help around the outside of the station.
宇航员可以在空间站内部操控它
It's usually controlled by an astronaut who's on the inside of the station.
加拿大臂2的两段都能适配这些抓取稳定装置
Either end of the arm can be attached to one of these grapple fixtures
这些装置在很多舱段上都有安装
that you'll find on various modules.
寻求号气密舱可以让宇航员安全走出舱外进行几小时的EVA
The Quest airlock allows the astronauts to safely step outside for a few hours to perform an EVA,
也就是太空行走
also known as a spacewalk.
然后是来自俄罗斯的舱段码头号
This is a Russian module called Pirs.
它可以作为太空行走的气闸舱
It can be used as an airlock for spacewalks
也可以作为来访空间站的飞船的对接口
or as a docking port to allow visiting spacecraft to attach to the station.
接下来开始建造综合桁架结构了
Now we get to start building the Integrated Truss Structure.
我之前提到过，综合桁架结构是ISS的“脊梁骨”
If you remember from earlier, this is kind of like the backbone of the station.
第一组是S0桁架，安装在命运号的上部
Our first piece is the S0 Truss, and it gets attached to the top of the Destiny module.
移动远距离维修基础系统(MBS)装在了S0桁架上
The Mobile remote servicer Base System, or MBS, was added next.
它能沿着桁架移动
This platform can move along the truss.
加拿大臂2安装其上后更是如虎添翼
It's especially useful when the Canadarm2 is attached.
接下来分别是S1桁架和P1桁架
Then the S1 Truss was added followed by the P1 Truss.
S代表右舵，P代表左舵
The S stands for starboard and the P stands for port.
这样你们就能分清左右了
This way, you know on which side of the station it's on.
每边都有放置三组散热板的空间
Each side has room for three more radiator panels.
但暂时每边只放了中间一组
For now, only the center ones will be installed.
外部储物平台2安装到了寻求号气密舱的旁边
ESP-2 was added to the station right next to the Quest airlock.
然后是装有太阳帆板、一组散热板的P3/P4桁架
This is the P3/P4 Truss segments with solar arrays and another radiator panel.
末端再装上很小的P5桁架
The tiny P5 Truss goes at the end here.
为了平衡空间站，我们要收起几个板子
To balance out the station, we'll have to retract a few panels.
接下来一年，另一侧的桁架也安装了上去
The following year, the other sides of the truss were added as well.
外部储物平台3装在这
ESP-3 goes down here.
然后P6桁架可以放置到它的最终为止了
And then the P6 Truss can be moved to its final resting place.
同时也可以展开其余的散热板了
It's also time to deploy a few more radiator panels.
和谐号，也叫节点舱2
The Harmony module is also called Node 2.
安装在命运号前部
It will be attached to the forward end of Destiny.
但我们要先进行一些调整
But first, we have to do some more rearranging.
和谐号有六个对接口，可以让空间站支持更多的拓展
Harmony has six docking ports which will allow for further expansion of the station.
接下来是哥伦布舱，它是来自欧洲的实验舱
Next comes the Columbus module, which is a European laboratory.
这时加拿大又来送机械臂了
Now we get some more robotics also built by Canada.
名叫Dextre，全称特殊微动作机械手
This is a space robot called Dextre.
它和加拿大臂2一样可以连接到抓取稳定装置上
It can attach to the same grapple fixtures that are used by the Canadarm2.
实际上，Dextre装在加拿大臂2的末端才能发挥最大功效
In fact, Dextre is most useful when it's attached to the end of the Canadarm2.
最大的舱段是日本实验舱，别名Kibo（日语中“希望”的意思）
The largest module is the Japanese Experiment Module, also known as Kibo(きぼう).
它分成几个部分安装到空间站上
It came up to the station in several pieces.
甚至还自带机械臂
It even has its own robotic arm.
终于，最后一个桁架——S6桁架到货了
Finally, we have the S6 Truss, the last of the truss segments.
终于看起来更像一个空间站了
Now we're starting to look a little more like the space station.
太阳帆板可以旋转从而对准太阳
These solar arrays will be rotated so that they face towards the sun.
使得太阳帆板可以产生更多的电力供给空间站
This helps the arrays generate more power for the station.
日本实验舱还有最后一部分要安装
The Japanese Experiment Module has one last addition.
名字叫日本曝露设施
It's called the Japanese Exposed Facility.
它能进行太空中的真空研究
This allows research to be conducted in the vacuum of space.
俄罗斯的舱段探索号和码头号很像
The Russian module Poisk is very similar to Pirs.
也能为俄罗斯的飞船提供对接口
It was another place for Russian spacecraft to dock.
“ExPRESS”全称
“Expedite the Processing of Experiments to the Space Station”
“空间站实验进程加速”
然后是第一个快速后勤运输工具(ELC-1)
This is the first ExPRESS Logistic Carrier, or ELC-1.
这里储存硬件设备从而让空间站正常工作
This is a place to store hardware to help the station work correctly.
ELC-2安装在桁架上部
ELC-2 was installed on top of the truss here.
宁静号，也叫节点舱3，安装在团结号的旁边
The Tranquility module, also known as Node 3, is added to the side of Unity.
宁静号下面安装着一个小舱段，叫穹顶舱
On the bottom side of Tranquility is a small room called the Cupola.
它有七扇窗户来看外面的景色
This has seven windows from which to see the view.
每扇窗户在不用的时候可以罩上
Each window has a cover that can be closed when they are not in use.
然后是俄罗斯的舱段晨曦号
Then came another Russian module called Rassvet.
它用于储存，还可以用于对接
This was used for storage and as another docking port.
列奥纳多号舱段用于储存给养与废弃物
The Leonardo module is used for storage of supplies and waste.
垃圾在这里储存最终带离空间站
The trash will build up here until it can be removed from the station.
然后是ELC-3、ELC-4
Here's ELC-3 and -4.
下面是名叫阿尔法磁谱仪的科学仪器
This is a science experiment called the Alpha Magnetic Spectrometer.
它用于研究诸如反物质等稀有粒子
It's used to study rare particles such as antimatter.
最近安装到空间站的舱段叫比奇洛充气式居住舱(BEAM)
A more recent addition to the station is called the Bigelow Expandable Activity Module, or BEAM for short.
发射时它只占很小一部分空间
It takes up a small amount of space during launch
而等安装到空间站后充气变大
and then inflated once attached to the station.
BEAM用于验证这类技术是否可行
BEAM is an experiment to see if this kind of technology can work.
ISS经费只够到2025年
The ISS only has funding through 2025.
但很有希望会继续下去
But hopefully, that will be extended.
之后，我们可能看到空间站某些组件会为其他项目而重新安装
After that, we may see pieces of the station repurposed for other projects in space.
字幕翻译给虫，欢迎投币点赞收藏分享转发评论关注充电~
感谢Patreon上的赞助者
I want to thank my supporters on Patreon for helping me make this video.
这不是我最后一次做ISS的动画视频
This won't be the last time you'll see an animation from me about the International Space Station.
请持续关注，可以在评论区告诉我下期想做什么
Stay tuned and let me know what you want to see next, in the comments below.
我是Jared Owen，感谢观看
I'm Jared Owen. Thanks for watching.